Jack Stachel Papers
Jack Stachel Papers
1943-1982
Stachel, Jack.
3 linear ft.
Correspondence, writings, speeches, clippings, printed matter, books and other material from the American Communist Party member and political activist.
4840101
Biographical History
Jack (Jacob Abraham) Stachel (1900-1965) was a Jewish-American political activist. A leader of the American Communist Party for forty years, Stachel was one of eleven Communist leaders convicted under the Alien Registration Act (popularly known as the Smith Act) in 1949, for which he served a sentence of five years in prison. Not only was Stachel involved in the progression of communism in America and the world, he also was outspoken on Vietnam, President Kennedy, the Civil Rights Movement, and other social and cultural shifts.
Stachel's wife, Bertha, was active as a Communist Party member by giving speeches, speaking out against the Smith Act verdict, endorsing Benjamin Davis, Henry Winston, and Gilbert Green, and wrote many letters to the editor of The Daily World, a communist leaning periodical. After Stachel died in 1965, Bertha annually published "In Memoriam" notices in The Daily World for more than ten years after Stachel's death.
Stachel and Bertha had one son, John.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Jack Stachel Papers consists of correspondence, memorabilia, and writings relating to the personal and professional life of the American Communist Party leader and his wife, Bertha.
Correspondence-subject files includes letters and greeting cards from fellow Communist Party members and committees and organizations related to Stachel's Smith Act trial. Some important individuals in this series are Gus Hall, Henry Winston, Benjamin J. Davis, and Eugene Dennis. There is a substantial amount of letters from Bertha to Jack while he was in prison from 1951 until 1955.
Memorabilia contains the couple's death certificates and correspondence related to their funeral and burial, as well as a small amount of miscellaneous material relating to Jack.
Writings are divided into items by Bertha and items by jack; these include letters to the editor, speeches, notes, and no on.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent. The other series are arranged alphabetically by title, type, or topic.
Separated Material
A number of books (21) have been separated from the collection and transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to and search on "Gift of John Stachel" to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Activism and social reform; Politics, government and public administration; Stachel, Jack.; Hall, Gus.; Baron, Rose.; Bedacht, Max, 1883-1972.; Bloor, Ella Reeve, 1862-1951.; Colón, Clara.; Davis, Benjamin J. (Benjamin Jefferson), 1903-1964.; Dennis, Eugene, 1905-1961.; Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley.; Ford, James W., 1893-1957.; Foster, William Z., 1881-1961.; Ganley, Nat, 1903-1969.; Gerson, Simon W.; Gibson, Lydia.; Hutchins, Grace, 1885-1969.; Johnson, Oakley C., 1890-; Rochester, Anna.; Russo, Mike.; Winston, Henry, 1911-1986.; Winter, Helen.; Goldwater, Barry, 1938-; Strauss, Franz Josef, 1915-1988.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Wallace, George C. (George Corley), 1919-1998.; Weinstone, William W. (William Wolf), 1897-1985.; Communist Party of America.; Workers Party of America.; Communism -- United States.; Labor unions -- United States.; Communist Trial, New York, N.Y., 1952-1953.; United States. -- Alien Registration Act, 1940.; Civil Rights demonstrations--1960-1970..; Civil rights and socialism.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Socialism.; Capitalism.; United States -- History -- 20th century.; United States -- Intellectual life -- 20th century.; United States -- Politics and government.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Speeches (documents); Poems.; Essays.; Clippings (information artifacts); Reports.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advance notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John Stachel, 2012-2013.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Family
    - Stachel, Bella (aunt), 1943 (Box 1)
    - Stachel, Bertha (wife)
      - to Jack, Jul 1951-Apr 1953; 7 folders (Box 1)
      - to Jack, Sep 1953-Feb 1955; 5 folders (Box 2)
      - to John (son), 1963; 1967,; 1975 (Box 2)
    - Stachel, Evelyn (daughter-in-law), 1953-1954 (Box 2)
    - Stachel, Jack
      - 65th birthday, 1965 (Box 2)
      - to Bertha and John, 1949 (Box 2)
    - Stachel, John (son), 1952-1953 (Box 2)
    - Stachel, Moishe (father), 1943 (Box 2)
  - Auerbach, Isabelle, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Baron, Rose, 1955-1956; 1960 (Box 2)
  - Bedacht, Max, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Birthday greetings, 1951-1960 (Box 1)
  - Bittelman, Mrs. Alexander, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Blair, Fred, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Bloor, Ella Reeve, 1949; 1982 (Box 3)
  - Colon, Clara, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Committee to Keep McCarthyism Out of Michigan by Fighting Smith Act Persecutions, 1953 (Box 3)
  - Communist Party USA National Election Conference, 1954 (Box 3)
  - Condolences on Jack's death, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Davis, Benjamin J., 1955 (Box 3)
  - Davis, David, 1954-1955 (Box 3)
  - Dennis, Eugene, 1952; 1956 (Box 3)
  - Doty, Orin, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Edwards, Richard, See Bloor, Ella Reeve.
  - Families of the Smith Act Victims, 1953-1954 (Box 3)
  - Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley, 1949-1950 (Box 3)
  - Foley Square Smith Act trial, 1948-1949 (Box 3)
  - Ford, James W., 1952 (Box 3)
  - Foster, William Z., 1950 (Box 3)
  - Ganley, Nat (Box 3)
  - Gerson, Simon W., See Foley Square Smith Act trial.
  - Gibson, Lydia, See Minor, Robert.
  - Gold, Michael, 1954 (Box 3)
  - Hall, Gus, 1966-1968; 1974 (Box 3)
  - Herman, V., 1960 (Box 3)
  - Hutchins, Grace, See Rochester, Anna.
  - Immigration case, 1951-1955; 1960-1962 (Box 3)
  - Janos, Gyetvai, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Jermoe, Victor Jeremy, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Johnson, Oakley C., 1965-1967 (Box 3)
  - Kettner, Otto, 1950 (Box 3)
  - Magil, Abe, 1956 (Box 3)
  - Minor, Robert, 1945-1950; 1954 (Box 3)
  - National Committee to Win Amnesty for Smith Act Victims, 1953-1954 (Box 3)
  - North, Joseph (Box 3)
  - Perloff, Jack and Ruth, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Rent Strike 203 W. 94th st, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Robinson, Dorothy, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Rochester, Anna, 1949; 1956 (Box 3)
  - Russo, Mike, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Schwartz, Sidney, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Shields, Art, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Trachtenberg, Rosalind, 1966; wife of Alexander Trachtenberg (Box 3)
  - United States v. Jacob Stachel, 1948 (Box 3)
  - Williamson, John, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Winston, Henry M., 1949; 1960,; 1966,; 1973,; 1976 (Box 3)
  - Winter, Helen, 1954 (Box 3)
  - Woodrow, Arley R., 1962 (Box 3)
  - The Worker Illinois Office, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1949; 1953-1957,; 1960,; 1964-1969,; 1974-1978 (Box 3)
- Memorabilia
  - Bertha Stachel, 1974; 1978-1979; death certificate and correspondence related to her funeral and burial (Box 3)
    See also In Memoriam" notice.
  - Jack Stachel, 1944-1946; 1966-1967,; 1979; death certificate and correspondence related to his funeral and burial (Box 4)
  - Jack Stachel, 1952; 1955; magazine clipping; photograph of Stachel (Oversize 1)
- Writings
  - Bertha Stachel
    - Letters to the Editor, The Daily World, 1954-1955; 1965-1967,; 1970-1974 (Box 4)
    - "In Memoriam" notice, 1969-1978 (Box 4)
    - Notes
      - 50th Anniversary International Women's Day, 1960 (Box 4)
      - on Benjamin J. Davis (Box 4)
      - on Henry Winston and Gilbert Green (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Poem "For Morton Sobell" (Box 4)
    - Speeches
      - Against the Smith Act verdict (Box 4)
      - On amnesty for Smith Act victims (Box 4)
      - Communist Party USA, 1973 (Box 4)
      - Jack Stachel, 1966; 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Jack's eulogy, 1966 (Box 4)
      - On the McCarrow Walters Act (Box 4)
      - William L. Patterson birthday rally, circa 1955 (Box 4)
      - [Untitled], 1953-1955; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Jack Stachel
    - Essays
      - About Communism [pamphlet text?], 1947 (Box 4)
      - Against Browderism, 1948 (Box 4)
      - "Improve Methods of Party Leadership" (Box 4)
      - New York Election, 1958 (Box 4)
      - The political situation and the progressive party, 1949 (Box 4)
      - "Relation of the Paper to Party" (Box 4)
      - "Social Democracy", 1956 (Box 4)
      - "Some notes on the program", 1954 (Box 4)
      - "Wallace and the third party movement", 1948 (Box 4)
      - "Youth", 1952 (Box 4)
    - Notes
      - 65th birthday (Box 5)
      - "81 Party Statement and Fight for Peace" (Box 5)
      - 1960 election (Box 5)
      - 1964 election (Box 5)
      - On Barry Goldwater (Box 5)
      - On capitalism (Box 5)
      - On Civil rights (Box 5)
      - On Communism (Box 5)
      - "Conference on the entire situation in SE Asia" (Box 5)
      - CP [Communist Party] meeting (Box 5)
      - CP [Communist Party] meeting report (Box 5)
      - The Daily Worker (Box 5)
      - On Defense Minister Joseph Strauss (Box 5)
      - "Importance of DuBois and Castro Declarations Adherence to Parties of M-L" (Box 5)
      - On Kennedy (Box 5)
      - Outline for an edition of The Worker (Box 5)
      - "Position of U.S. Capitalism and the Kennedy Administration" (Box 5)
      - "Social Democracy-Reform" (Box 5)
      - Speech to Communist Party (Box 5)
      - Speech on Gates (Box 5)
      - On Vietnam (Box 5)
      - "Why a Quarterly and its Character" (Box 5)
      - "Winning Mass Influence" (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
      - [Untitled], 1945 (Box 5)
    - Reports
      - CPUSA [Communist Party of the USA], 1949 (Box 5)
      - To Communist Party plenum, 1949 (Box 5)
      - "Remarks of Jack Stachel re: the Worker Campaign", 1944 (Box 5)
      - On The Worker and The Daily Worker, 1957 (Box 5)
    - Speeches
      - CPUSA [Communist Party of the USA], 1957 (Box 5)
      - CPUSA [Communist Party of the USA] conference, 1947 (Box 5)
      - On CP [Communist Party] (Box 5)
      - History of CP [Communist Party] given at the Youth Project (Box 5)
      - Strike struggle (Box 5)
      - On Will Weinstone (Box 5)
  - Jack and Bertha Stachel
    - Poems (Box 5)
    - Fragments (Box 5)